<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full and true account of the sad and dreadful fire which happened in the borough of Southwark on the 22 of September, 1689 ... and the manner of seizing a notorious papist.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2310A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25435</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08959047</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08959047</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42097</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42097)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1284:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full and true account of the sad and dreadful fire which happened in the borough of Southwark on the 22 of September, 1689 ... and the manner of seizing a notorious papist.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: Torn with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fires --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>Southwark (London, England) --  Fire, 1689.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42097:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Full and True ACCOUNT Of the Sad and Dreadful FIRE Which Happened in the <hi>Borough of Southwark,</hi> On the 22 of <hi>September</hi> 1689. Between the Hours of One and Two in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the manner of Seizing a Notorious <hi>Papiſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <add>24. Sept. 1689.</add>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ON the 22d of this Inſtant <hi>September,</hi> about Two of the Clock in the Morning a Light, more than ordinary, was eſpied in a <hi>Stationer's</hi> Shop in the <hi>Rules</hi> over againſt the <hi>King's-Bench</hi> Priſon in <hi>Southwark;</hi> which increaſing more and more, gave a Suſpicion to the Watch, and Others, that it could be no Candle: But whil'ſt they were Intentive to conſider it, they pla<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly perceived the Houſe was on Fire; proceeding thereupon to give Notice to the Family, and ſorce the Doors, In hopes to quench it before it could get any Head, but their Endeavors proved ineffectual<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for no ſooner it got Air, but burſting out at the Windows, it raged with ſuch vehemency, that all which could be done, was the ſaving of the Peoples Lives. When having conſumed that Houſe, with the Goods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Furniture, it took hold of the next; and ſo making its progreſs on the Weſt-ſide of <hi>Southwark,</hi> where Booths for Shows are placed in the Fair-time, notwithſtanding extraordinary ſhowres of Rain had fallen before, it caught hold of the Deal boards, and fi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the Booth called <hi>Parker</hi>'s <hi>Booth,</hi> and ſo the adjoining Timber; which falling to the Eaſtward, fired the other ſide of the Street. And both at once bei<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g in a Flame, not only much hindred People from paſſing with their Goods, but increaſed the Conſternation: For the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings being Timber for the moſt part, and generally old, with many intricate Alleys running backward, the Flame, driven on by the Wind, raged extremely, notwithſtanding Endeavors that were uſed on all Hands to ſuppreſs it. Whereupon, leſt the other Booths taking Fire, ſhould aſſiſt it in its progreſs, they were ordered to be pulled down, and, accordingly, many of them were overthrown, and the Boards and Rafters removed, when about Three of the Clock part of the <hi>King's-Bench</hi> Priſon took Fire, which cauſed a great Cry amongſt the Priſoners; and ſuch as had their Lodging in the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part of the Priſon were removed backwards: But 'tis credibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, during the Conſternation, two or three of them made their Eſcapes amongſt the Crowd.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:42097:2"/>
            <p>The Engines being by this time brought, and a great number off Hands employed, only the Front of the Common Side of the Priſon received Damage, yet the Fire on both ſides the way not only ſpread in the Front North and South, but with great Vehemency burnt backward; ſo that the Inns, known by the Signs of the <hi>Falcon,</hi> and the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> were flaming both at once, the quantities of Hay and Straw cauſing them to blaze in a terrible manner, and ſheets of Flame broke off, and carried by the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wind ſcorched, and much endangered the Houſes at a very conſiderable diſtance, ſo that Powder being brought, Order was given for the blowing up ſuch Houſes as ſtood moſt convenient to give the Fire a Check which was accordingly done, and the Pipes cut to ſupply the Buckets and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, many of the Soldiers Quartering thereabouts uſing Indifatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Induſtry; not only in Suppreſſing the Fire, but in helping the diſtreſſed People who ſeemed every where to be in a Hurry and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion to carry off their Goods: For the Terror of the Rageing Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſuch, that it ſeem'd to Threaten at a great diſtance, which cauſed the People accordingly to make a timely preparation for a Removal; but by blowing up, and the Interpoſition of ſome ſtrong Brick houſes whoſe Walls ſtopped the Flame; about Four of the Clock it began to Abate, and ſo by degrees the Fuel on which it fed being Conſumed, and the Wind ſlacking, between Five and Six of the Clock it was brought under, and a Stop put to its further Progreſs.</p>
            <p>In this Lamentable Fire which laſted about Four Hours, between. Fourſcore and a Hundred Houſes are Reckoned to be Burnt and blown up, Beſides a great many Shattered and Defaced, the loſs of Goods of divers kinds is held to Amount to an Extraordinary Value, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Families by reaſon of the Swiftneſs of the Fires Progreſs having no time to Remove, Eſpecially any thing Conſiderable. How it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan whether by the Careleſneſs of a Candle, or otherways, Remains doubtful Reports and Conjecturals being various: As likewiſe doth the Burning of the Child in the Houſe where it firſt began, ſaid to be left in the Cradle through haſt and forgetfulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That which is obſervable is, That there was one Man, who was heard to be liberal in his Tongue, above all others, in ſpeaking ſuſpicious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting Words; whereupon he was preſently ſeized, and brought before Mr. Juſtice <hi>Evans,</hi> and upon Examination was found to be a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> having Crucifixes, Beads, and other Trinkets about him, and therefore was committed Priſoner to the <hi>Marſhalſea.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Licens'd</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 23d 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_quack">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>☞ In <hi>Plow-Yard</hi> in <hi>Grays-in Lane,</hi> lives Doctor <hi>Thomas Kirleus</hi> a Collegiate Phyſician, and Sworn Phyſician to <hi>Charles II,</hi> until his Death: Who with a Drink and Pill, hindring no Buſineſs, Cures all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers, Scabs, Scurfs in the Face, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: Kings-Evil, Leproſie, and Venereal Diſeaſe, expecting nothing if he Cures not. Of the laſt, he hath Cured above 500 perſons in this City, many after Fluxing. It quickly and ſafely Cures it in the beginning, which cannot be done with <hi>Mercury,</hi> without danger of Life. The Drink is 38. the Quart, the Pill <hi>1 s.</hi> the Box, which is two Purges. They excel all Purges in cleanſing all Crudities and Impurities, and ſo prevent and Cure many Diſeaſes, and eſpecially the Gout and Stone. In all Diſeaſes he gives his Opinion for nothing, and his Medicines for little.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. R.</hi> near <hi>Fleet-bridge.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
